<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Linux Lemming</title>
    <link>https://linuxlemming.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Linux Lemming</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 14:46:19 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://linuxlemming.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LIVE</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/upcoming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 14:46:19 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/upcoming/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Hosted Image Sharing Made Easy</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e06/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 19:21:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e06/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PEBCAK and Covid</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e05/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 09:39:47 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e05/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PEBCAK and Covid</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/e05/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 10:25:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/e05/</guid>
      <description>Check out the Podcast that accompanies this blog too! Where are my Episodes? My release schedule was recently disrupted due to illness. Luckily I have been healthy but members of my family and academic institutions they attend were impacted by the Covid pandemic. Thankfully, no one in my family contracted Covid, but we had to practice quarantine procedures to keep ourselves and our community safe. This took time away from the project and something like this may occur in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helping the Hippo</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e04/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 08:12:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e04/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helping the Hippo</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/testingweek/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 14:54:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/testingweek/</guid>
      <description>Ubuntu 21.04 Testing Week Oh boy! What an oppertunity! I just heard from many different podcasts about the beta test week for Ubuntu 21.04. I have never participated in an event like this before so I am grateful that something like this exists.
Alan Pope recently made a forum post about the event that includes documentation for new testers. It&amp;rsquo;s about an hour investment to learn the process of how to conduct the tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lemmings Do Have Something to Contribute!</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 20:04:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e03/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributions</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 15:19:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Contributions On This Page Go From Most Recent in Descending Order Podcast Generator- Helped to create and publish more detailed installation notes.
Linuxserver.io- Provided more detailed installation notes about the use of docker-compose and bash aliases.
Castanet Hugo Theme- Worked with Matt on my gitlab instance and he added this addition afterword. Also, put in a PR to have the show added to his readme.
Mealie- Wrote up how iOS shortcuts can be used with the application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Hosted Podcast Generator</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/pg/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 19:42:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/pg/</guid>
      <description>Moving from Gitlab to Podcast Generator A few years ago, a friend and I had what I would call a &amp;ldquo;hobby cast&amp;rdquo;. We would put together show ideas, meet up once a week and record a 30-60 minute show. It was a lot of fun and I used the open source software Podcast Generator to publish it in iTunes so our friends could subscribe and listen.
I remember the installation process being really easy so I figured I would go a head and try to get it up and running for the Linux Lemming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Some SWAG on a RPI 4</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e02/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 19:39:04 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e02/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with a New Server</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/e02/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 15:21:46 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/e02/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE 3/17 Ok so I made this post and podcast last week but a lot changed. First, after I got everything working it all fell apart after 24 hours. SSD died and I had to order a new one. I got a 2TB spinning USB 3.0 drive and still had to do do Ubuntu 20.10.
Also, my revised LSIO documentation was Accepted and MERGED!! Hooray, first big LL win!
Original Post As I was setting up new things, I stumbled across a redditor asking for help with SWAG and NextCloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git, VSCode and Contributing to the Linux Lemming</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e01/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e01/</guid>
      <description>Special Thanks Matt Stratton for his hard work on the castanet theme which drives this site and to rwaltr for his awesome video on using Gitlab to create a website using Hugo. Also, the DLN Crew for their weekly spotlight on Git which motivated me.
Original Documentation Written documentation for getting started with building a simple blog lives here
How to Contribute to the Linux Lemming A detailed blog post will be made for this but in this episode I go over how to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributing to the Linux Lemming</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/contributing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 12:59:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/contributing/</guid>
      <description>Contributing Links The easiest way to contribute to the project would be to submit links to the resource page. As submissions come in, they can be organized a bit more but for now, anything goes.
I have come to really like VSCode, so that is my preferred way to interact with Git and what this guide covers.
This guide assumes the following:
 Reader has an account on Gitlab Reader has VScode installed Reader understands some Git Basics  Fork the Project After you are logged into gitlab, the project needs to be forked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources Used for the Linux Lemming Podcast</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/credits/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/credits/</guid>
      <description>Music Intro Music- An Example For by Captive Portal Out Track- Boss Splash by sawsquarenoise Album art may not be accurate. Could not easily resize using links provided by the free music archive.
Art Episode 06 Art- Found on the Bristol Penguin Archive Project
Episode 05 Art- Found on Wikimedia Commons by user Sarah Klockars-Clauser . Flickr Account
Episode 04 Art- Found on Greg Leden&amp;rsquo;s Blog
Episode 03 Art- Image by OpenClipart-Vectors from Pixabay</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 02:11:48 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/resources/</guid>
      <description>Resources from the Linux Lemming Linuxize- Simple website with good information.
 I really enjoy their commands section. They also have in-depth articles as well. This site often comes up when searching the internet.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prepare to Launch</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/e00/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 13:18:30 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/e00/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Who am I?  Long time Linux Desktop user and new to the server realm. Hobbyist who knows enough to start projects but doesn&amp;rsquo;t have enough free time to maintain or spend hours troubleshooting. A &amp;ldquo;lemming&amp;rdquo; who appreciates concise, up to date documentation and wants to see more of it widely available. Avid podcast listener.  What Will This Project Be Like?  Place for people to listen/read to my journey via podcast and blogs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting the Framework for Community Contribution</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/podcast_assets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 16:12:58 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/podcast_assets/</guid>
      <description>Getting Involved I would love people to submit work to the project or ask someone to attempt a project and report back on their process.
In order to do this, there has to be a rigid methodology so that a user knows how to ask and what to present. I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with a few ideas that still need some testing but I think it is a good place to start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Woes</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/website/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 13:42:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/website/</guid>
      <description>Ignorance Is Not Bliss- Have Some Grit When Using Git I think I was a little over ambitious with this project. I am fine using git in a terminal but when working with markdown files, I like to have a preview pane so I chose to try to do everything in VSCode. Installing the app wasn&amp;rsquo;t an issue, but I had a lot to learn in terms of using it with github and gitlab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Things in Order</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 14:15:27 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/blog/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Why bother? Yet another drop in the ocean right? Well, I guess this is an outlet for me and something I love doing so why not? I did do a brief podcast with a friend of mine called Let&#39;s Learn Something New and cut my teeth on podcasting there. I put time and energy into getting a small mixer, condenser mic, learning Ardour with the help of someone I met online, learning how to use a publishing program, having intro/outro clips, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcasts</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/other-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 15:18:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/other-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>Linux Unplugged A great virtual Usergroup for those interested and experienced with linux. Participation can be done through mumble
Selfhosted A podcast focused on self-hosting from the Jupiter Broadcasting network.
Ask Noah Show A weekly call in show that talks about how to do all the things &amp;ldquo;they&amp;rdquo; said couldn&amp;rsquo;t be done on linux and teach you how to do the same. Active participation can be done through Matrix or you can call in and listen or join the queue to ask questions at 1-855-450-6624</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RastaCalavera</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/host/rastacalavera/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 20:55:58 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/host/rastacalavera/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been hammering on Linux since 2002, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been serious about using it since 2009. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a desktop user and only got into server side linux in 2014. KDE and XFCE are my main desktop environments and I primarily run an Ubuntu base (although I do try Arch variants once in a while.) Since getting into server side linux, I&amp;rsquo;ve really focused on self-hosting simple things. This was, and still is, a steep learning curve for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Did This All Come About?</title>
      <link>https://linuxlemming.com/tll/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2016 02:11:48 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://linuxlemming.com/tll/</guid>
      <description>The Linux Lemming Origin Story I&amp;rsquo;ve been using the linux desktop off and on since about 2007. In 2009 I went linux full time and haven&amp;rsquo;t looked back. In 2013 I started to get more interested in server side linux but I didn&amp;rsquo;t get too serious about self-hosting until 2018.
Over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot but I am still learning new things constantly. One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve struggled with is documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
