Hello and welcome to the Linux Lemming. I'm your host, Rasta
Calavera. We're going to have two parts to this episode.
I'm going to start by talking about some podcast 2.0 features, and then I'm going to dive into the
project Link Ace, which is a really cool, self-hosted, link archiving bookmark manager type thing.
So, I should have chapters, so if you want to skip ahead, I'm not
going to stop you. I highly encourage it. That's why I make chapters.
Alright, so let's talk
about podcasting.
I've been struggling
recently with chapters.
I had this big crusade on how to use Audacity's label export as the starting point to convert
that tab separated text file into a podcasting 2.0 compliant JSON file for podcast chapters.
And it was a huge
pain in the butt.
I really wanted to try to stick to command line tools. I thought that
would be the best way, and I went down this huge rabbit hole with that.
The first one I went down was trying to figure out how to use the cut command, because you have
three columns of text, two of those columns are timestamps, and they're identical to each other.
So, I don't need one of them, so I wanted to remove one, cut it out.
So, cut seemed like the right thing to do, and it was pretty easy.
But now, once I have this two column text, the timestamps go out way too far. I only
need to a whole number, and they go out, let's see, two, four, six decimal places.
It does count in seconds to the whole second, which is
nice, but I don't need six decimal places after it.
So, then I was trying to figure out how I could do that. There's
probably a way to do a delimiter cut, but I couldn't figure that out.
It'd be nice if I didn't have to
do two commands, like cut, cut.
But I played around with AWK. I don't know if it's called AWK or
whatever, but I was trying to use these two different tools, SCD or AWK.
They're both command line tools, and they're super complicated. They're very powerful
things, but reading the documentation, the man pages, it was a lot to digest.
And when you try to look up how to do different things like this on Stack Exchange or
Stack Overflow and things like that, the conversations get real heavy real quick.
But I did find a way to use AWK to accomplish what I wanted, where
you get seconds to the whole number and your title for the label.
But you have to declare how
many rows you have in there.
So, like, if I have seven rows, and on each row I have a time and a title,
then in the command I have to do $3, $4, repeat all the way up to seven.
And that will give me what I want, but I don't
want to have to type out how many rows I have.
So, it was an imperfect result.
And then once I even got that, I still got to convert it
all into JSON. And you got to do, like, a loop through it.
And I was trying to figure
out how best to do that.
And I knew that bash tools or command line
tools would not be a great way of doing that.
So I'd have to change to either JavaScript
or Python or some other language.
And, you know, it's been a long time since I've
really tried to code. Loops are always a thing.
So I was just stuck trying to figure out how I could loop through with
these two different things that I needed to put into a JSON format.
But I did find some shoddy Python that, well, it's not shoddy. I made it
shoddy. I found Python examples where people had done similar things.
And I played around with that for a couple days and learned
about, like, Python dictionaries and lists and stuff like that.
And I got it to a point where it was putting out close
to the format I wanted, but with excess information.
And that was because it was using,
like, the dictionary in Python.
It was adding, like, a whole extra piece in the JSON
file, which I think is called the declaration.
Dictionaries need, like, two parts. And I can't
remember if it's like statement and something else.
Or no, it's key. Key and whatever
that dictionary input is.
And the key that it kept spitting out, I didn't want a
key. I just wanted what was inside of the dictionary.
So I learned that Python dictionaries is not
what I wanted to do to make a JSON file.
I had been, you know, publicly working through
this problem on my Git lab page and everything.
And I actually had a couple of contributions, people coming in and
saying they were going to take a look at it and things like that.
But I actually, I went to Reddit
and I posted some stuff there.
And people were mentioning pandas and different
JSON packages and libraries that could be used.
And that was really helpful to kind of send me down my way
to look for ways of approaching this and to solve this.
You know, when somebody just gives you a little bit
of a push, like, hey, you could explore this tool,
that gives me another thing to put into my Google string
and just get closer and closer and closer to find somebody
who has already asked a very similar thing that I can
benefit from and try to use and mold into my situation.
So the Reddit was good. And I made
a lot of progress with that.
But then I actually, so a while ago I found
this project and it was a Jekyll project.
So I didn't pay it much mind because
I don't use Jekyll, I use Hugo.
But user Penguin999 created this podcast template
to create a podcasting website using Jekyll.
It's a static site generator
just like Hugo is.
But he had some very
advanced features in there.
You could put your mp3 file, your show notes, your cover
art, and then you have to make a metadata file in JSON.
But once you make all these things and
you drop them in a very specific folder,
as Jekyll goes through the CI CD, well, I guess not Jekyll, as GitLab
goes through the CI CD build process to create your Jekyll public site,
it will actually take all of that
information and put ID3 tags into the mp3
and output a JSON with all of
that information in it as well.
So really cool stuff.
It also generated a blog post, put a lot of page information above
the embedded player for this project and different things like that.
It did a lot of things that I don't need, but it also
did the few crucial things that I really want and need.
So I decided, you know what, instead of scouring, I'm just going to really try to
dig into what already exists here and see if I can make it work for my use case.
And I think I have.
So, oh, and a big thing about this, too, is it was designed to work with
the Audacity label exports, and you don't have to do anything with it.
It can work with the
three columns just fine.
So this was like the goose
that laid the golden egg.
So Penguin 999.
Thank you very much
for your hard work.
I'll probably try to reach out just to let you know I'm
benefiting from this and using it and I'm very grateful.
There's no license
in the project.
I assume it's GPL.
But yeah, there's
no license here.
And actually funny thing, too, when I was having the issues with my server not being able
to stream MP3s to podcast players and it was like messing up all the times and everything.
I had found, I believe
it was Penguin 999.
He had raised an issue specifically with the GitLab team about rate limiting with GitLab pages and how they need to
be engineered a little bit differently so that people can stream from a GitLab page specifically for a podcast.
So small world, Penguin 999 feels all
my struggles has gone through them.
So maybe I need to reach out and get in touch and
we can, you know, cheers to figuring stuff out.
So I tinkered with this Python file and it was really just a lot of cutting things out, trying to
run it, see what broke, read the error outputs, try to troubleshoot that and rinse and repeat.
And then once I got something working close to how I needed it,
then I could try to trim out all the other little extra fluff.
Like if there's quotation marks that I don't need or
if I need to rename something a little bit different.
And I'm finally in a good place with it and I'm going to
use it to try to produce this episode when it's all done.
So the workflow as it is right now is I need two folders
and they can be new folders or I can use existing folders.
But one of them is a source and inside of this source, I
have to have my art, my MP3, my JSON and my chapters.
And they all need to be named
using a three digit format.
So this will be episode nine.
So it'll be two leading zeros and
a nine for all of those files.
And then once I have all those in there, I run the Python script and it does its
magic with all the Python libraries and everything else to modify the MP3 file,
to put that chapter art into the MP3, to put the tags into it for each
chapter, to put myself as the author, the title of the episode, all that.
So really cool stuff.
Saves me a step from using Easy Tag to do some of that or when I export out of my
DAW, whether that's Arduer or Audacity, this just does it, boom, one time done.
And it does it in everywhere
that it needs to happen.
So that's great.
So I'll try to do
that with this.
And a cool thing that you can do to verify that the MP3 actually has the tags, and I read this
somewhere when I was searching, is you can use FFMpeg to read all the data on that file.
And it'll tell you whether or not
there are actually chapters in there.
Because I was having a heck of a time finding
a podcast player on Linux that would show it.
Rhythmbox doesn't show chapters,
VLC didn't show chapters.
So I'm not really sure what players are going to take advantage of this,
but it's kind of nice to have chapters done both ways pretty painlessly.
So hopefully with this, maybe in, I know, Pocketcast,
they support chapters, so maybe this will show up there.
And also I just found out, what is
the name of this app I downloaded?
I downloaded Cast-o-Matic and it says right in there that
it does support podcast 2.0 and embedded MP3 chapters.
So I don't know which it'll show me in Cast-o-Matic,
but it supports both, which is kind of cool.
Oh, and I guess the one last thing, when you get the
JSON file from the output, it's all on a single line.
So I have to open that in Visual Studio Code and then
right-click and format the document and then just save it.
So that's one other little thing to kind of
point out there if you want to try this.
But yeah, I threw out my work on Mastodon, you got a couple re-blogs
and favorites and stuff, but it didn't bring me any contributors.
Maybe that's a network effect
with GitLab or whatever.
And my one other participant who was going to jump in, trail's gone cold,
but I mean, it's been holidays and crazy times and everything else.
So maybe they'll come back, maybe the work that I've thrown
together will make their contribution a lot easier.
Oh, another cool thing, you can easily put in the strings for
URL and image if you wanted to add images to your chapters.
I don't really want to do that, but it's a cool thing
to have there if I ever felt like I needed to.
So there is that.
All right, well, I guess that's going to take us to the end of
podcasting 2.0 stuff and we'll transition over to LinkAce.
All right, so LinkAce is a self-hosted tool
that provides a way to archive a website.
You can add tags to this archive and you can even put it into
like an organized list and it all lives inside of a dashboard.
It's just this really cool way
of keeping all your things.
If you can imagine how you keep bookmarks in a traditional browser,
you can put it in folders, you can do different things like that.
I believe you can even tag it in Firefox
and Chrome, but it's not archived.
So if that website goes dead,
your bookmark is useless.
This archives it.
So you've got it forever, which
is huge, really, really cool.
And you can actually make your dashboard of your collection
of links, your archive of links, public if you want.
And when you bookmark things in the future, when you
do that, you can say whether it's public or private.
So if you want to have things public, if you're sharing it as like a group or whatever, but once
in a while you want to keep something just for you, you can do that, which is pretty neat.
So if you want to explore this project,
there are two options to set up LinkAce.
There's a simple and the advanced and the main difference
between them is how the database backend connects to it.
The creator of the project recommends that if you have full control of your system, and you're
not limited to a lockdown or constrained environment, then you should do the advanced.
Otherwise, the simple
should be used.
Now I personally chose to go the simple
route because I was just testing it.
But maybe if I notice any like performance hits or
something, I'll migrate to the advanced setup.
But just for myself, I'm running the
simple and I've been really enjoying it.
So the installation process for this is you pull
down the different stuff from their GitHub account.
You have to unzip it, and then it's a Docker compose. So you got to go into a dot
and v file, fill out the different fields in there that need to be customized.
And then once you're done with that, it's a
Docker compose away to bring up the stack.
Now because I use a proxy, and I wanted to have this
exposed so that I could access it from anywhere.
I also had to put in a network section to make sure that it
ran on the same Docker network as my LSIO swag reverse proxy.
And I documented that in the blog
that'll go along with this.
So if you're in a situation where the information for linkage does not live on the same
compose file as your reverse proxy, this is how you get the networks to talk and connect.
Now originally, I had been using linkage a long time
ago, probably like, I don't know, a couple months ago.
And then stuff happened and I couldn't get it
back up by migrated systems and everything.
And I thought I was going to have to start completely from scratch
because I didn't think I had the environmental file anymore.
But it turned out I was being ridiculous and it's a dot file. So unless you
LS tack a or show dot files in the file browser, you're not going to see it.
And it was there the whole time. So I was
able to bring back my old installation.
I did have a little bit of a permission issue, but you know, because
it's just my stuff, I just chmoded at 777 and called it a day.
And it worked fine. Don't do as I do. Troubleshoot
your permission issues and do it the right way.
But once it got up and running, I was exploring
some of the features a little bit more.
And you can do two factor off, which
I thought was really intriguing.
And I hadn't tried this at all. And you can actually
use bit warden to generate the two factor code.
So I was like, whoa, this is awesome because I use
bit warden every single day, I pay for their plan.
It says project I absolutely love to support,
but I've never tried the two factor off.
And this was a great opportunity. So I gave it a whirl
and it worked amazing. It works really, really well.
It has a feature where you can like scan
a QR code to make the two work together.
I couldn't get that part to work, but you can put
the token that it creates in there manually.
And once I did that, I was on a roll. So now I have a self hosted
application with two factor authentication, which is amazing.
It's tied into my my password
manager. So that's pretty cool.
The app also has an email tie in which I get really confused when it comes to email
because I use Google and they don't support the direct SMTP protocol anymore.
You got to create a specific app
token and do all this other stuff.
Other projects have documented that. I believe it was
caliber caliber web had pretty good documentation on that.
This project didn't specifically
call out how to use Gmail.
And it was kind of convoluted when I was trying to remember, I
didn't want to go back and try to dig up the other project.
Now that I remembered it's caliber, I think it was, I could potentially go
back, but I remember having to do these weird things in the web browser,
and then having to copy and paste different things
and then do it in the container environment.
We had to exec into the container, paste some things,
get another token to make it all talk together.
And it was just
very, very hacky.
I didn't remember how to do it.
So I don't have email working with link
ace, but I don't really think I need to.
I think this is a really cool project.
I think it's worth checking out.
Some other bookmarking things people have thrown
out that I've seen are surely that's a big one.
And I haven't really, I haven't played with
those ones, but I really enjoy link ace.
I think it's done really well.
There's browser integration.
You don't have to
install an extension.
It's just a really easy drag
this to your bookmark bar.
And then whenever you want to bookmark something,
you click it and it does it and it works fantastic.
I also created an iOS shortcut so I can do
that from my iPhone and send things to it.
It's really awesome.
So if you're interested in archiving
different things, check it out.
Highly recommend it.
And that will bring us to
the end of this episode.
I've been your host,
Rasta Calavera.