Hello, and welcome to another
episode of the Linux Lemming.
I'm your host, Rasta Calavera.
I was really hoping to do a live
recording with this episode.
It was going to be kind of the whole focus,
and it kind of fell flat on its face, so we
will revisit the hows and whys of that
happening in just a moment here.
All right, so let's talk about getting lit,
and the lit LIT stands for Live Item Tag.
So this is a podcast 2.0 namespace, and it's
something that you can put in the RSS feed
of your podcast to let the new podcast 2.0
apps know that you are going live, and you're
doing a live recording, or a live
broadcast, not a recording.
And the only podcast that I'm subscribed to that
actually makes the use of this is podcasting
2.0.
I think it's a really cool feature, it
makes me really excited about podcasting.
But I think more and more content creators
will support this in the future, but it is
a bit burdensome to wrap your head around it,
especially if you're somebody like myself
who watches all this stuff vicariously on
the side, and then tries to figure out how
to do it all, having no coding background, and
this is very limited knowledge on programming
languages and things like that.
It truly is running the scissors,
I got a lot of cuts tonight.
But you know what, I think I figured out some
of the basic steps, so let's walk through
what that is.
Okay, so step one, you need to get a server that
will allow you to broadcast a live stream.
There's probably easier approaches to this,
maybe there are servers out there that will
let you create an account and let you,
you know, hop on them as needed.
I am self-hosting, so I am using an application
called AzuraCast, and this is an internet
radio station, and it has a live
DJ live broadcast feature.
So that is the application that I am running
on my server to actually get audio out and
available in the wider internet,
and let's take a look.
Is anybody currently listening?
No.
Which I don't blame you, because right now I
just have a loop of Adam Curry saying this
lovely little clip of audio.
I screwed it up already, I can't
figure anything out anymore.
Because I literally can't figure anything out
anymore, I got kind of stuck in a rabbit
hole this evening.
Oh boy.
But so anyway, AzuraCast is doing the broadcasting
of all of that, and how I'm sending the audio
from my local laptop machine to my headless
server running AzuraCast is using a software
called Mix with 3X's.
Again, I picked this because it was pre-installed
on my machine with my distro of Zoran, so
why not?
And it was pretty straightforward to connect
the two pieces together, so I'm happy enough
with that.
Now the next step is adding the lit tag to
the RSS feed, and I wasn't sure originally
if this had to live inside of the tag for an
individual episode, or if this lived outside
of that overall item tag, and I compared a
couple different feeds, and I finally figured
it out, ran it through a validator and everything,
and it has to live outside of the item tag.
And how it's actually added into my RSS feed
is a little complicated, because I'm using
Hugo Static Website Generator, and
I'm using Castinet as the theme.
I had to play around with the actual, well,
two main files, the episode RSS XML in the
Castinet theme, and also the
default config.toml file.
So in the Castinet episode RSS XML file, right
below the description of my podcast, I had
to put in the podcast live item tag, and within
that first line, it had to have the status,
so whether it is ended, live, or pending, it
also has to have a start and an end time.
And those three things, it pulls
from the config, the config.toml.
I mean, I guess you could come in here and
manually put those in, but my thought process
was I only want to touch a single file, so I
could touch the config file to put in those
three things pretty easily, and then just
push that up to the site, rather than having
to go through all the folder structure of
themes, Castinet, layout, you know, all the
way down to find the actual file every single
time, I could just go to my config and put
it in.
And then there's some other fields, too, and
these all remain static, so there's like
a title, so I just called it
the Linux Lemming Livestream.
There's the enclosure URL, which is the
URL to the stream from Azure Cast.
You have to say what type it is and the length of
it, and I had to do a little bit of a conversion
from kilobytes to bytes for the
length, nothing too complicated.
And then you close it out with a podcast content
link, which is basically the same link as
above in the enclosure URL,
I'm pretty sure that's okay.
That might be if maybe you're using alternate
enclosures, maybe you had other types of streams
like a Vorbis stream or an Opus stream or something
like that, you'd have a couple different
things, but I only have the one,
keeping it as easy as possible.
Then you close that out with
a podcast live item tag.
So yeah, in the config file then, I just have
three things that I added under the main params
section.
I added a show live status, and again, I can
have three different values pending live
or ended, show live start, and this needs
to be in an ISO 8601 extended format.
So I put a link in my file that's available on
GitLab for everybody to see, just a website
that'll do that
conversion for you.
So you put in like the date and the time of when
you plan on the stream starting and ending
and then it converts it and then
you just copy and paste it over.
So easy peasy.
So once that technical stuff is
out of the way, you publish it.
So it goes to the website, the RSS
XML refreshes, everything's updated.
The next step is to send off a pod ping, which
will update the podcast index to let everybody
know that you're live basically, and it should
send a thing to all of the podcast players
and everything
else and whatnot.
And I got some help with this.
I kind of reached out on Mastodon and other
places, and the millennial media offensive
gave me a Python script that I used, and it
said feed is marked for immediate update.
So seemed like that worked.
But then when I checked the podcast index
and everything, didn't say that I was live.
I didn't get any
notifications in Podverse.
So I don't know
what that's about.
There was another way, Stephen Bell from,
I don't know if he is directly associated
with Sovereign feeds, or if he
just had the suggestion of it.
But there's a website called sovereignfeeds.com,
and you can look up your RSS feed.
It's basically a standalone RSS feed editor,
and you can add podcasting 2.0 tags to your
feed from that.
You can also send pod
pings from that.
So I sent a pod ping, and you have to solve a
little captcha, and it was like, all right,
we're going to send
this for an update.
But then, I don't know, I never got
an update, which is confusing to me.
But when I ran it through the XML, through
the Livewire podcast validator, it said that
I have four podcast
names based tags.
I have the content link, I have the live item,
the transcript, and the chapters, and they're
all green.
So I've done it appropriately.
So I don't know what the missing part is,
but you know what, it doesn't really matter
that much because I can't have my microphone
go to both Audacity and Mix at the same time.
So even though I have a looping live stream
and nobody's listening to it, it's not really
a value anyway because
my voice isn't on it.
So I'll probably have to reach out to the
community and get some help to figure out
how I can do some
audio routing.
But yeah, the coding and stuff, it
was just a lot of trial and error.
Wasn't super horrible,
you know, to figure out.
I don't know, I got to learn more about GUIDs
and how to have that per episode and for the
podcast as a whole because I feel like that
would be like a good logical next step would
be doing something
with the GUID.
So that's going to be
where I'm headed.
But actually, you know what, as long as we're
talking about podcast 2.0 tags, we should
just go right into what I've
been doing with chapters.
Oh my goodness.
So I started an issue on my GitHub about how
one could take a chapter file from Audacity
and well, I guess it's a label.
They don't call it chapters because you can
put labels into Audacity and then you can
export all your labels with timestamps
and it's like a tab separated text file.
So you can get this like nice little output
and it's a three column output and it's like,
you know what, I should be able to take this
text file and convert it into a JSON to use
it for the chapters
for podcasting 2.0.
That would make a lot of
sense, like this should work.
It was way more complicated
than I wanted it to be.
I wanted to just use built in bash
tools to edit the text and everything.
But I very quickly learned that you got to
use something more robust like Python.
That's where I eventually
landed on it.
And I had another community member kind
of hop in and try to help out Eric.
Eric seems like a
really cool dude.
He's active on the mastodon.
He's the host of our podcast and I started
listening to that recently since he's helping
me out.
Just kind of like check out that little
area where he is and it's pretty cool.
He uses the castnet theme
too and everything.
So Eric and I were kind of going back and forth
on different approaches for how we could
accomplish this because I assume he uses Audacity
as well and he's interested in the podcasting
2.0 namespace.
And so, you know, we both have
something we want to solve.
So awesome to work together
to try to solve the problem.
And you know what?
That's really the whole value for
value mantra, time talent, treasure.
He was giving me some time and some talent
to just even reach out and say, hey, yeah,
let's work on this.
I might be able to help out.
So I did a lot of tinkering with
it, a lot of different approaches.
And I eventually landed on
a good enough solution.
So basically, I took, I found some different
examples of Python scripts online and I mushed
them into one file.
So I bring in two libraries,
import CSV and import JSON.
And when you get your export from Audacity,
your text file, the first step is to get
you to trim away the
first column of text.
And you can do that just
using like a bash tool.
So I would use something like to just
get rid of that first column of text.
And then I want to find a cleaner way to round
out the values just to the nearest whole number.
That might be something
to do with AWK.
I'm not quite sure on that, but cut is just
a clean, easy way to get rid of that first
column of numbers so that you're just
left with start times and titles.
And then in your file, you have to add headers
of start time and title to your text file
because that's needed
for the final JSON.
So once you've done that to your text file,
then you're ready to start launching this
Python script that I kind
of mushed together.
So it loads two libraries, it then will open
up the text file and you have to put in the
proper name of the text file.
So you need to have an established naming
scheme if you don't constantly want to change
things inside of
this Python script.
So it opens your text
file, it reads the items.
The first thing it does is it finds all of
the tab spaces and cuts the tab space and
replaces it with a comma and then it will save
that file as a CSV file and then it will
open up that CSV file and it pulls
everything into a JSON array.
And then once you've got this whole JSON array
going in, it will strip everything out, create
the new file and then spit it
out to where it needs to be.
So the very last step then is once you have this
JSON file, you just need to add the versions
and the chapters to the
top of the header.
And so that's where I'm at right now with
getting chapters easily created and not having
to do too much by hand.
Ideally it'd be nice to automate the entire
process, but I just don't have the coding
background and the knowledge to do easy loops
through all that stuff because how I envision
it actually working is you'd export your text
file and it would have the name, episode,
E, number, number, number, three digit number
and then you drop that into a folder and then
the second it's dropped into the folder, your
machine is aware like, oh, time to convert
this and then it just does everything for
you and you get the JSON file and then you
throw that on the website and
link to it and everything.
So that would be the
ideal flow for that.
So yeah, maybe Eric will come in and do some
looping magic and get that all to be awesome
and hopefully I'll figure out this whole lit
business because I think it'd be pretty cool
to just do a little live broadcast pretty
easy, but I got to figure out pod ping and
I got to figure out my audio routing I guess,
it's just kind of a little bit of a, not great
with that.
All right, well that brings us to the
end of this episode of the Linux Lemon.
Oh, that is weird, it's only
coming in a single channel.
Okay, wow, let's see here, hmm, hmm, hmm,
hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm,
hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm, hmm.
says it is sending a pod ping live pod ping
sent the other one marked for immediate update
I don't know how to like verify anything with
that but who knows we'll see okay well a lot
of new things going on tonight it's not
very scientific change all the things and
complain when it doesn't work goodness
goodness goodness okay keep that up so I
kind of see if anybody does get on
to the channel see if it's live
I wonder why those are gray that one's not maybe
the newest one is always one up hmm hmm hmm okay
we're gonna talk about the blogs and the kit lab
is organized these tabs here oh yeah I don't have
the when a mix going because it keeps crashing
with audacity let's see if I can get mix up and
running does not like to play kindly with
audacity unable to open error opening okay yep
because audacity is using the mobile pre USB audio
so let's okay well crashed let me reconfigure you
mix let me change my inputs man retry after fixing
the issue reconfigure get help exit yes I would
like to reconfigure please but it all just crashes
oh good god alright turn the recording back on
so going going lit live item tag is I don't know
it's probably not gonna work but got some some
good leads as to why so let me catch everybody up
on what's going on issue number one audio routing
so I have a microphone going into a mixer and then
I have two balanced quarter inches to a three
and a half millimeter stereo jack output from
the mixer that I'm putting into an M audio USB
interface that connects to the computer and when
I have two software stacks open audacity and mix
they can't pull from the same source which is
crazy to me and I don't know if that's because
I'm not using jack and I'm just using the default
also I think I feel like if I was using jack I
should be able to patch in the microphone input
to both applications but as it stands I cannot
oh no parsing error that's not good what did I
break man so I ran my XML through a validator
for the RSS feed and it said my live item was
wrong when I looked at the example compared to
mine I had a closing out tag in the very first line
there and when I look at how it should be set
up from the bare bones example there's just a
closing greater than bracket and so that's what
I did but it doesn't look like it helps hmm
all right podcast live item status got that
got that got that just a closing bracket and
I've got the title the enclosure URL make
sure that looks the same closure URL it's
got a forward slash greater than closure
yep yep and then double enclosure podcast
live item at the end yep now when I had the
slash in there I didn't get this error hmm XML
parsing error not well formed status there's
an ampersand is that what it's yelling at me about
well that would be in my config so that's the live